Herbert Thoms collection
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
Herbert Thoms collection
1906-1971
Ms Coll 14
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
11
(4 archival letter boxes, 3 tall legal boxes, and 4 flat boxes)
Thoms, Herbert, 1885-1972
Biographical / Historical
Herbert King Thoms, M.D. was a Yale obstetrician, historian of medicine, and artist/engraver. Born in 1885 in Waterbury, Connecticut, his early education was acquired at the Vermont Academy and the Waterbury High School. He received his M.D. from Yale in 1910. Following internships at the Backus Hospital in Norwich and Memorial Hospital in New London, he served as an assistant resident at the Sloane Hospital for Women in New York City. Then, having decided to specialize in obstetrics, he spent a year at the Johns Hopkins Hospital. In 1915, he returned to New Haven where he began an active practice in obstetrics. He was appointed an associate clinical professor of obstetrics and gynecology at Yale, and in 1927 he became a member of the full-time faculty. He became chairman of the Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology in 1947, a position he held until his retirement in 1953. During his academic career, he made many important contributions in his field including studies in pelvimetry, the plan for infant "rooming-in" after delivery in conjunction with Dr. Edith Jackson and members of the Department of Pediatrics, the "natural child birth" program, and studies in the Yale infertility clinic which he established. As a teacher, he was influential in bringing to the attention of his students the importance of a humanistic approach to medicine. Throughout his career he was a prolific author of books and articles on the history of medicine. His special interest was the early history of Connecticut medicine. In addition to his clinical and historical activities, he found the time to become an accomplished artist and engraver.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of correspondence, particularly a set of letters from Grantly Dick-Read; a nearly full set of articles by Thoms; and 11 scrapbooks and photograph albums concerning his years as a Yale medical student and early faculty member, his work on natural childbirth and rooming-in, and his interest in the history of Connecticut medicine.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Custodial History
The collection was donated at various times by Herbert Thoms.
Infertility; Medicine -- Connecticut -- History; Natural childbirth; Obstetrics; Obstetrics -- History; Newborn infants -- Care; Pelvimetry; Correspondence; Photographs; Scrapbooks; Physicians -- Connecticut; Obstetricians -- Connecticut; Medical historians -- Connecticut; Beaumont, William, 1785-1853; Dick-Read, Grantly, 1890-1959; Eliot, Jared, 1685-1763; Fairbairn, John Shields, 1865-1944; Beaumont Medical Club; Grace-New Haven Community Hospital; Yale University. School of Medicine; Yale University. School of Medicine. Class of 1910
- Correspondence, Series I
  Scope and Contents
  The correspondence represents materials that Thoms selected for the Library. Former Librarian of the Historical Collection, Madeline Stanton, wrote on one envelope of letters, "Letters that Dr. Thoms thought of some interest & importance & had therefore saved. Brought to H. L. [Historical Library] Nov. 1964."
  - Letters from Grantly Dick-Read, 1947-1957 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Correspondence on natural childbirth and training for childbirth. There is one letter from Thoms to Dick-Read. Includes carbon copy of G. Dick-Read, "Reply to the critique by the editors of the Obstetrical and Gynecologial Survey...upon a contribution by Herbert Thoms and Robert H. Wyatt,...to American Journal of Public Health, 1950, 40: 797," January 1952.
    One letter dated March 27, 1950, was added to this folder in 2014.
  - Letters from John S. Fairbairn, 1923-1939 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Correspondence from Fairbairn, an obstetrician at St. Thomas's Hospital, London, on obstetrics and the relationships among midwives, obstetricians, and gynecologists in England. Thoms met Fairbairn on his 1923 trip to England.
  - Correspondence, 1935-1946 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Correspondence folders contain both letters received and carbons of Thoms's replies. Correspondence has been arranged by date and consists mainly of letters from obstetricians regarding pelvimetry and natural childbirth.
  - Correspondence, 1947-1949 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1951-1955 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1956-1959 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1961-1963 and no date (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Typescripts and miscellany, Series II
  - Typescript: Recollections of travel to England, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Typescript: "Professor Stromberg's Visit to New Haven", 1923 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Professor Gustave Stromberg of the University of Upsala, Sweden, was invited to speak before the New Haven Medical Association on December 15, 1923. The typescript tells an amusing story that Madeline Stanton, Librarian of the Historical Library, declared to be "a fine old hoax perpetrated by Dr. Thoms."
  - Typescript of "Pioneers in Medicine at Yale: A Profile Study", no date (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Typescript of "Expectant Parenthood", ca. 1964-1972 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Typescripts of articles: "Our Taller Girls and Childbirth" and "Understanding the Adolescent Girl", no date (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Typescripts of historical articles, no date (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Includes: "The Redemption of Ezra Budlong" (poem); "Anton Chekhov--Writer and Physician"; "Emerson, Prophet of Atomic Warfare"; "The Thomas Ruggles' of Guilford"; "Yale Places Memorial in Guilford Cemetery"; and "The Versatile Doctors of Yale College, 1701-1815."
  - Almanac for Academics by T.G.B. with Illustrations by Herbert Thoms (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Given by Lucia Fulton to Madeline Stanton, July 1960.
  - Small engravings by Herbert Thoms (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Eleven original engravings and two cards with photographic copies of engravings. Several engravings were Christmas cards.
  - Additional small engravings by Herbert Thoms (Box 1, Folder 18)
    These five small engravings were donated by Dr. Michael Kashgarian in 2015. They were removed from frames.
  - Service award from Connecticut Medical Services, Inc., 1969 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Connecticut Medical Services was a progressive health insurance organization begun in 1949. CMS celebrated its 20th anniversary in part by sending plaques to long-term physicians in the system. The letter with the plaque was dated August 27, 1969 and was signed by John M. C. Betts.
- Natural childbirth and rooming-in: Minutes, articles, and clippings, Series III
  - Natural Childbirth Study Committee minutes, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Minutes of three meetings at Grace-New Haven Community Hospital and a copy of a letter from Kate Hyder, Associate Professor of Gynecologic and Obstetric Nursing, Yale School of Nursing.
  - Review of Thoms's books, 1934-1962 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Folder contains mostly clippings from professional journals reviewing Thom's books, especially his Training for Childbirth: A Program of Natural Childbirth with Rooming-In (1950) and Understanding Natural Childbirth: A Book for the Expectant Mother (1950).
  - Newspaper clippings on natural childbirth and rooming-in, ca. 1947-1951 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Newspaper clippings on natural childbirth and rooming-in, ca. 1952-1957 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Articles on natural childbirth collected by Herbert Thoms, 1939-1953 and undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
    See also Herbert Thoms's own articles in Box 4.
  - Articles on rooming-in collected by Herbert Thoms, 1950-1966 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Contains professional and popular articles. See also Herbert Thoms's own articles on these subjects in Box 4.
  - Articles on natural childbirth and rooming-in from the Medical Library's pamphlet files, 1938-1952 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    The Yale libraries, including the Medical Library, collected pamphlets on various subjects up to the mid-1960s.
- Published articles, 1910-1971; Series IV
  General
  These were donated by Thoms to the Library and numbered by Madeline Stanton, Librarian of the Historical Collections. "Bibliography of Herbert Thoms" was published in the "Herbert Thoms Number," Yale Journal of Biology and Medicine, 25(6) (June 1953): 461-467. With the articles is a folder of Thoms and Stanton's notes on his bibliography. With Thoms's help, Stanton drafted a bibliography through 1960. Folders contain professional articles on obstetrics, articles on history of medicine, and popular articles.
  - Madeline Stanton and Herbert Thoms's notes on his bibliography, 1964-1971 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Articles, 1910-1914 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Articles, 1915-1919 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Articles, 1920-1924 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Articles, 1925-1927 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Articles, 1928-1929 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Articles, 1930-1932 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Articles, 1933-1934 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Articles, 1935-1937 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Articles, 1938-1939 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Articles, 1940-1942 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Articles, 1943-1944 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Articles, 1945-1946 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Articles, 1947-1949 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Articles, 1950-1951 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Articles, 1952-1953 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Articles, 1954-1955 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Articles, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Articles, 1957-1958 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Articles, 1959-1960 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Articles, 1969-1971 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Scrapbooks, Series V
  - Yale scrapbook, 1906-1910 (Box 5)
    Scrapbook created when Thoms was a medical student at Yale. Like many other medical students in this period, Thoms had not attended a college. The medical school experience became like a college experience. The scrapbook has clippings and memorabilia on Yale sports, music, and other campus activities, as well as medical school materials. Thoms graduated from Yale School of Medicine in 1910.
  - Yale and professional scrapbook, 1910-1932 (Box 6)
    Includes reprints, invitations and announcements, and clippings related mostly to his professional activities. Of note is his opening of an office in New Haven in 1914 and a brochure, Some Rules for Pregnant Women, by Herbert Thoms, M.D. Organizations represented include the Connecticut State Medical Society, the New York Obstetrical Society, the American Gynecological Society, Nu Sigma Nu, and the Beaumont Medical Club.
  - Scrapbook of clippings about natural childbirth, 1947-1950 (Box 7)
    Scrapbook of newspaper clippings related to Thoms's pioneering program at Grace-New Haven Hospital to train women for "natural childbirth" (i.e., without anesthetics).
  - Scrapbook of magazine articles on natural childbirth and rooming-in, 1947-1950 (Box 8)
    At the same time as Thoms was training women for natural childbirth, Edith Jackson, M.D., and members of the Yale School of Nursing were pioneering the practice of "rooming-in" whereby the newborn remained in the hospital room with the mother.
  - Scrapbook: "Medical Landmarks in Connecticut, Vol. I" (Box 9)
    Thoms was interested in the history of medicine from the beginning of his career. This scrapbook contains photographs by Thoms of homes and memorials related to early Connecticut physicians, along with Thoms's lengthy labels on the physicians. Names include William Henry Welch, Reuben Smith, Samuel Seabury, Erasmus Darwin Hudson, Elisha North, Simeon Smith, Oliver Wolcott, Seth Bird, Elihu Hubbard Smith, Samuel W. Gold, and Daniel Sheldon. Thoms's scrapbooks on the history of medicine appear to date from the 1950s.
  - Scrapbook: "Medical Landmarks in Connecticut, Vol. II" (Box 9)
    Scrapbook contains more photographs, mostly taken by Thoms, of monuments, homes, and buildings related to early Connecticut physicians. These are accompanied by typed labels. Among the homes and memorials covered are the Stafford Springs House, Laboratory of Applied Physiology (Yale), Elisha Perkins House, Governor Peters House, William Tully House, Alcott Schoolhouse, John Winthrop Memorial, Alexander Wolcott House, Horace Wells Memorial, The Parsonnage (Canterbury), William Beaumont Homestead, Noah Webster House, Benjamin Silliman House, Gaylord Farm Sanatorium, Timothy Dwight College and memorial to Eli Ives, 150 York Street (former home of the Yale School of Medicine), Blue Hills Hospital, Joseph A. Barratt Memorial, William Beaumont Memorial, Thomas Miner birthplace, Horace H. Hayden Memorial, and the Elnathan Chauncey House.
  - Scrapbook: "Medical Landmarks in Connecticut, Vol. III" (Box 10)
    Scrapbook contains more of Thoms's annotated photographs on landmarks related to Connecticut medicine. Photos include the Philip Turner House; home of Eli Todd; Chester Hunt medical office; birthplace of James Gates Percival; Connecticut Agricultural Experiment Station, 1958; the Institute of Living; Lyman Hall Memorial; Blue Hills Hospital; Shaw Mansion (Nathaniel Shaw Perkins); Meigs-Bishop House, Stokes House (Faculty Club, where Clifford Beers and others founded the Connecticut Society for Mental Hygiene); Joseph W. Alsop House; Daniel Lathrop House; David Bushnell Memorial; Rufus Blakeman House; and home of Benjamin Silliman (Fairfield).
  - Scrapbook: "William Beaumont Memorial, Lebanon, Connecticut" (Box 10)
    Scrapbook containing articles, letters, and photographs concerning physician and physiologist William Beaumont (1785-1853), and the dedication of a memorial in his birthplace of Lebanon, Connecticut on June 29, 1926. The Beaumont Medical Club at Yale played a major role in establishing the memorial. The scrapbook also contains memorabilia on other memorials to Beaumont.
  - Jared Eliot Scrapbook, Volume I (Box 11)
    Scrapbook containing labeled photographs, copies of letters, and newspaper clippings concerning the eighteenth-century Connecticut minister/physician and agriculural improver, Jared Eliot (1685-1763), an early graduate of Yale College.
  - Jared Eliot Scrapbook, Volume II (Box 11)
    Scrapbook containing the labelled photographs that Herbert Thoms took of Jared Eliot's home in Guilford, the restoration of his tombstone, and tombstones of members of Eliot's family.
  - Scrapbook of newspaper articles on Thoms's engravings (Box 11)
    Thoms was an accomplished engraver who exhibited his works locally. He especially created etchings and charcoal drawings of Yale buildings, Connecticut buildings and landscapes (among them early physician's homes), and sailboats. The Historical Library holds several examples of Thoms's artwork.